Hello, welcome everybody. How is everybody doing today? This is going to be an
안녕하세요, 여러분 모두 환영합니다. 오늘 다들 어떠신가요? 이번 수업은
awesome listening and speaking class. I'm so glad that all of you are here. Welcome
정말 멋진 듣기 말하기 수업이 될 겁니다. 여러분 모두 여기 와주셔서 정말 기쁩니다. 모두
everybody. See the screen. All right. Now? Yes. Okay. So remember, good
환영합니다. 화면 보이시죠? 네. 좋습니다. 자, 기억하세요, 좋은
communication starts with good listening, being an active listener means showing
의사소통은 좋은 경청에서 시작됩니다. 적극적인 경청자가 된다는 것은 여러분이 몰입하고 있다는 것을
you're engaged. Sometimes we listen quickly for the main idea and that's our
보여주는 것을 의미합니다. 때때로 우리는 요점을 파악하기 위해 빨리 듣는데, 그것이 우리의
fast and intuitive thinking and other times we need careful analytical
빠르고 직관적인 사고방식이고, 다른 때에는 신중하고 분석적인
listening and that's when we really kind of pick things apart and try to
경청이 필요합니다. 그때가 바로 우리가 사물을 정말로 세세하게 분석하고
understand the deeper meaning of those things. So we need to practice both types
그것들의 더 깊은 의미를 이해하려고 노력할 때입니다. 그래서 우리는 두 가지 유형의 경청을 모두 연습해야 합니다.
of listening to understand the superficial level of things in the meaning and
사물의 피상적인 수준의 의미를 이해하고,
to understand (the) deeper analytical level of things. When you practice a lot, you get
사물의 더 깊은 분석적인 수준을 이해하기 위해서요. 연습을 많이 하면,
the hang of it and you don't have to kind of deliberately seek to understand it
요령을 터득하게 되고, 그것을 이해하기 위해 일부러 그렇게까지
so much. You'll just understand and it will become more intuitive with time but
애쓸 필요가 없어집니다. 그냥 이해하게 되고 시간이 지나면서 더 직관적이 될 것입니다. 하지만
it's always good to analyze first. So we'll listen as the scenario is read
먼저 분석하는 것은 항상 좋습니다. 자, 여기 시나리오를 읽을 테니 잘 들어보세요.
here. I want you to listen to it twice with different focuses and I'm trying to
다른 초점을 두고 두 번 들려드릴 텐데, 제가 여러분이 이해하지 못할 수도 있는
show something that you might not understand. So don't feel bad if you don't. Okay.
무언가를 보여드리려고 합니다. 그러니 이해하지 못하더라도 너무 속상해하지 마세요. 알겠죠?
All right. Okay, team. For the new project, I need everyone to synergize their
네. 좋습니다, 팀원 여러분. 새 프로젝트를 위해, 모두 화요일 업무 종료 시까지
deliverables by COB Tuesday and ensure proactive stakeholder engagement. Make it
결과물이 시너지 효과를 낼 수 있도록 협력하고 통합해주시기 바랍니다. 선제적인 이해관계자 참여를 보장해주시고요.
snappy. Did you understand? The main idea, but there are some new words
신속하게 처리해주세요. 이해하셨나요? 요점은 알겠지만, 새로운 단어들이 좀 있네요.
others are okay. Okay, so you have some experience which is great. You've got the
다른 것들은 괜찮습니다. 네, 어느 정도 경험이 있으시군요, 좋습니다. 우리가 무언가를 끝내기 위해
main idea that we need to work together to get something done but there might
함께 일해야 한다는 요점은 파악하셨지만, 여기에는 여러분이 이해하지 못하는
be some things here that you don't understand. Which words are hard for you to
몇 가지 사항이 있을 수 있습니다. 어떤 단어들이 이해하기 어려우신가요?
understand? So the words that I don't understand are
제가 이해하지 못하는 단어들은
synergize and snappy. Okay, so to synergize something is basically to make
'synergize'와 'snappy'입니다. 네, 무언가를 'synergize'한다는 것은 기본적으로 서로 협력하여 더 큰 효과를 내도록 하는 것입니다, 그렇죠?
things in sync, right? When things are synchronized, they're synergized. They
요소들이 함께 작용하여 시너지 효과를 내면, 그것들은 'synergized'된 것입니다. 그것들은
work well together, right? So we need everybody to basically come together and
함께 잘 작동합니다, 그렇죠? 그래서 우리는 기본적으로 모든 사람이 함께 모여
agree on what deliverables, what needs to be produced by Tuesday, and to make
화요일까지 어떤 결과물, 즉 무엇이 생산되어야 하는지에 대해 동의하고, 'make it snappy'는
it snappy is to do it quickly. Oh, okay. When you're talking.
그것을 빨리 하라는 뜻입니다. 아, 그렇군요. 말씀하실 때
You're using that word, right? Oh, make it snappy.
그 단어를 사용하시는군요, 그렇죠? 아, 'make it snappy'(빨리 해).
All right. So let's listen to a short scenario and imagine you're in this
네. 그럼 짧은 시나리오를 듣고 여러분이 이 회의에 있다고 상상해보세요.
this meeting. If you were to hear that in a meeting, what would you
회의에서 그런 말을 듣는다면, 이해하기 위해
do to interrupt to try to understand? If you had some sort of question, you have
어떻게 말을 끊고 이해하려고 노력하시겠어요? 만약 어떤 질문이 있다면, 요점은 파악하셨죠?
the main idea, right? But you wouldn't probably want to listen to what comes next a
하지만 아마도 다음에 나올 말을 좀 더 듣고 싶으실 겁니다.
little bit. How would you ask for clarification?
어떻게 설명을 요청하시겠어요?
Well, as you mentioned, everything is about listening. So I think I will wait the
음, 선생님께서 말씀하신 것처럼, 모든 것은 경청에 관한 것이죠. 그래서 저는 그 사람이 말을
person to end what that person is (going to say)? And if I don't understand, then I will go
마칠 때까지 기다릴 것 같아요. 그리고 만약 이해하지 못하면, 그때 가서
and like, hey, I need clarification on this part of what I just say.
"실례지만, 방금 말씀하신 이 부분에 대해 설명이 필요합니다."라고 할 것 같습니다.
So you would wait for the person to finish saying what they want to say.* And that's because
그러니까 상대방이 하고 싶은 말을 다 끝낼 때까지 기다리시겠다는 거군요. 그건
you don't want to be rude or interrupt anyone when they're talking. Yes. Actually, I always
누군가가 말하고 있을 때 무례하게 굴거나 방해하고 싶지 않기 때문이시죠. 네. 사실, 저는 항상
tried to wait because you need to know what the person is thinking and not just to think like
기다리려고 노력해요. 왜냐하면 상대방이 무슨 생각을 하는지 알아야 하고,
that's what you're saying. So it's good not to make assumptions. I agree. And it's great to wait
단지 그렇게 말씀하신 것만으로 이해해서는 안 되니까요. 네, 추측하지 않는 것이 좋습니다. 동의합니다. 그리고
for those pauses in speech and conversation to know when we can ask for clarification.
말이나 대화 중에 잠시 멈추는 순간을 기다렸다가 설명을 요청할 수 있다는 것을 아는 것이 좋습니다.
Okay. So how do we interrupt politely? That's part of what we're talking about today.
네. 그럼 어떻게 정중하게 말을 끊을 수 있을까요? 그것이 오늘 우리가 이야기하는 내용의 일부입니다.
Asking for clarity. They're useful phrases. Well, I would say, excuse me,
명확성을 요청하는 것. 유용한 표현들이 있습니다. 음, 저는 "실례합니다,"
what's like, that would be a good example.
라고 말할 것 같아요. 그게 좋은 예시가 될 것 같네요.
So I will say, excuse me, I just would like to know what you are trying to say when you are
그래서 저는 "실례합니다만, 이 계약에 대해 말씀하실 때 무엇을 의미하시는지 알고 싶습니다."
talking about this contract or something like that. Okay. So I need more clarification on these
와 같이 말할 것 같아요. 네. 그래서 이 주제들에 대해 더 많은 설명이 필요합니다.
subjects. All right. It's very formal. I like that.
알겠습니다. 매우 정중하시네요. 마음에 듭니다.
Yes, we need to... that's like our environment when we talk with we have our meetings.
네, 저희는... 그게 저희가 회의할 때 대화하는 환경과 같아요.
We can make* jokes outside, you know, but then we are with the meeting where we need to try to be
밖에서는 농담을 할 수 있지만, 회의 중일 때는
a really like professional. You can be more casual outside of the meeting, but in the meeting
정말로 전문가처럼 행동하려고 노력해야 합니다. 회의 밖에서는 더 편하게 행동할 수 있지만, 회의
itself, it's time to be professional and formal. All right. So this language register is really
자체에서는 전문가답고 격식을 갖춰야 할 때입니다. 네. 그래서 이 말의 격식은 정말로
a bit formal and also intonation is important. You know, sounds rise and they fall too. So an
다소 격식 있고, 억양도 중요합니다. 아시다시피, 억양은 높아졌다가 낮아지기도 하죠. 그래서
example would be sorry. Could you please repeat the part about COB or could you repeat the part
예를 들면, "죄송합니다. COB에 관한 부분을 다시 한번 말씀해주시겠어요?" 또는 "make it snappy에 관한 부분을
about making it snappy? What does that mean? All right. So now notice that we use could here and could
다시 말씀해주시겠어요? 그게 무슨 뜻인가요?" 와 같이요. 네. 이제 여기서 'could'를 사용했다는 점에 주목하세요. 'could'는
is considered more polite than can. So could is a little bit more formal and then can is a little
'can'보다 더 정중한 표현으로 간주됩니다. 그래서 'could'는 조금 더 격식 있고, 'can'은 조금
bit more casual, although you can use either one. Someone is not being disrespectful if they use can,
더 편한 표현이지만, 둘 다 사용할 수 있습니다. 누군가가 'can'을 사용한다고 해서 무례한 것은 아니지만,
but if you want to show more formality, it's better to use could. Here's another example.
더 격식을 차리고 싶다면 'could'를 사용하는 것이 좋습니다. 여기 또 다른 예시가 있습니다.
This time I would like for you to try to raise the intonation at the end. So is that right?
이번에는 끝부분에서 억양을 높여보도록 하세요. "Is that right?"(그게 맞나요?)처럼요.
All right. Is that right? Can you, can you read this part here?
네. "Is that right?"(그게 맞나요?) 여기 이 부분을 읽어주시겠어요?
If I understand correctly, you're asking us to, is that right?
제가 제대로 이해했다면, 저희에게 요청하시는 것은... 그게 맞나요?
Is that right? Yeah. And here's another example. We're working a lot. Is that right?
그게 맞나요? 네. 그리고 여기 또 다른 예시가 있습니다. 저희가 일을 많이 하고 있죠. 그게 맞나요?
We have to come in this weekend. Is that right? All right. How about this one? Can you read
이번 주말에 출근해야 한다고요. 그게 맞나요? 네. 이건 어떠세요? 이 부분을
this one for us? Could you please explain what you mean by snappy?
읽어주시겠어요? "snappy"가 무슨 뜻인지 설명해주시겠어요?
Uh-huh. Very good. Hi, snappy. Well, snappy means it should be different.
네. 아주 좋습니다. 안녕하세요, 'snappy'요. 음, 'snappy'는 빠르고 재치 있다는 뜻입니다.
Well, no, I think that's fine. We can use, for example, like the one you said COB because
음, 아니요, 괜찮을 것 같아요. 예를 들어, 선생님께서 말씀하신 COB처럼 사용할 수 있습니다. 왜냐하면
there are some people* that don't know what COB means. You could just simply ask, could you
COB가 무슨 뜻인지 모르는 사람들도 있으니까요. 그냥 간단하게 "snappy가 무슨 뜻인지 알려주시겠어요?
tell me what snappy means? I don't know this. It's a new word for me, you could say.
저는 이걸 몰라요. 저에게는 새로운 단어예요."라고 말할 수 있습니다.
You know, I think sometimes we feel embarrassed when we don't know something.
아시다시피, 때때로 우리는 무언가를 모를 때 당황스러워하는 것 같아요.
And so we don't want to ask, we don't want to admit, but it's okay to clarify.
그래서 묻고 싶지 않고, 인정하고 싶지 않지만, 명확히 하는 것은 괜찮습니다.
The whole purpose of communication and business is to understand and be understood.
의사소통과 비즈니스의 전체 목적은 이해하고 이해받는 것입니다.
And a key takeaway from this slide here is basically we use could to make polite requests.
그리고 이 슬라이드의 핵심 내용은 기본적으로 정중한 요청을 할 때 'could'를 사용한다는 것입니다.
You can use discourse markers like excuse me or if I understand correctly you're asking
"Excuse me"나 "If I understand correctly, you're asking..." 또는 "you're telling us that's right"와 같은 대화 연결 표현을
or you're telling us that's right and then rephrasing what they say. Those are really great ways to
사용하고, 그들이 말한 것을 다시 한번 말하는 것입니다. 그것들은 정말 훌륭한 방법입니다.
ask for clarification. All right. So go ahead, I'm sorry.
설명을 요청하는 데 있어서요. 네. 그럼 계속하세요, 죄송합니다.
No, maybe before I didn't use to do that, but now like I feel more confident to ask for
아니요, 예전에는 그렇게 하지 않았을지도 모르지만, 지금은 단어의 의미를 묻거나
the meaning of the word, to (know) what they're saying. So we know what they're exactly there trying
그들이 무슨 말을 하는지 알기 위해 질문하는 데 더 자신감을 느껴요. 그래서 그들이 정확히 무엇을 전달하려고 하는지
to communicate. Yeah... it only gets better with time.
알 수 있죠. 네... 시간이 지나면서 더 나아질 뿐입니다.